<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pastors last legacy and counsel delivered in a farewel sermon, preached at St. Philips in Bristol, August 24th, 1662 / Mr. Edward Hancock ...</title>
            <author>Hancock, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45488</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40546</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19356013</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19356013</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108768</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45488)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108768)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1672:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pastors last legacy and counsel delivered in a farewel sermon, preached at St. Philips in Bristol, August 24th, 1662 / Mr. Edward Hancock ...</title>
                  <author>Hancock, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, XIII, 11 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Farewell sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108768:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108768:1"/>
            <p>THE Paſtors laſt Legacy AND COUNSEL.</p>
            <p>Delivered in a Farewel SERMON, Preached at St. PHILIPS in <hi>Briſtol, Auguſt,</hi> 24<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1662.</p>
            <p>By Mr. <hi>Edward Hancock,</hi> late Miniſter there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:108768:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108768:2"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Edward Hancock's</hi> Farewel: being his laſt Sermon, Preached at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Philips</hi> in <hi>Briſtol, Auguſt, 24. 1662.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SEt your hearts to hear the words of the Lord, for it is not a vain thing, becauſe it is your Life: as it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the 13<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> Chapter of the ſecond Epiſtle of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and the 11<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> Verſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally, my Brethren, farewel: be perfect, be of good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, be of one minde, live in peace, and the God of love and peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>YOu know at this time I am called to do a work which poſſibly may be unpleaſing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many of you, even as to my ſelf; which work is indeed a ſtrange work: that is, to dye a civil death whilſt I am naturally alive. When the Sun for this day is ſet, I ſhall then ceaſe from having any charge over you, and you will then ceaſe from having me to be your Miniſter. I may ſay as one did that was going to dye a violent death; I am this day to do a work that I never yet did, I deſire of God to give me ſtrength that I never yet had.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:108768:3"/>
            <p>And having been long upon this Text, ſhewing to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of you your ſeveral duties, and my time allotted draws nigh to an end: The Lord grant that it may be ſpent for your eternal good, that ſo I may dye well in this reſpect amongſt you.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that dye well do uſually theſe five things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Firſt, They muſt endeavour to make their peace with God.</item>
               <item>2. Secondly, To be in perfect charity with all men.</item>
               <item>3. Thirdly, To ſet their Houſe in order.</item>
               <item>4. Fourthly, To give good counſel to their ſurviving Friends.</item>
               <item>5. Laſtly, To commend them all to God by Prayer.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, As to my peace with God, in reference to my civil life, although yet naturally alive, I think I may in ſome meaſure ſay with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the 20th. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and the 27. <hi>verſe,</hi> I can give up my account with joy, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the diſcharge of my duty, I having kept back nothing from you of the Councel of God, having taught you publickly both in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon the Oracles of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Thoſe that dye well ought to dye in perfect charity with all men. I hope I do ſo truly, having not the leaſt thing againſt any man this day. I was not born a man of ſtrife actually, whatever I have been paſſively: I have been ſevere againſt your Sins, though not againſt your Perſons. I am in charity this day with every mans Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, though not with their Sins: I have not ſtriven againſt your Perſons, but againſt your Sins, and the Devil. I now dye amongſt you in perfect charity with all men, deſiring the Lord to forgive all mine enemies, as I do from my ſoul forgive them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:108768:3"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Thoſe that dye well muſt ſet their houſe in order; that is a work that ſhould not be put off until the laſt gaſp; the houſe that I have to ſet in order is not my own, but the Lords, it is good to do it timely: you know I have made it my work for theſe two Moneths paſt to ſpeak to the ſeveral ſorts of people in my Congregation, and to ſhew unto every one his duty, and how each parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Man and Woman ought to behave themſelves both towards God and Man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, Thoſe that dye well, muſt give good counſel to their Friends; the Lord grant that the words that I have ſpoken, and am this day to ſpeak, may be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and practiſed by you. The words of dying men are uſually remembred. Oh! that the counſels I am now to leave with you may take ſuch deep impreſſion in your hearts, that they may never be forgotten. I ſhall take up the greateſt part of my time with counſel unto you all, and then ſhall conclude all with the Bleſſing in my Text, <hi>The God of love and peace be with you all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with counſel unto you all in general, and what I ſay to one I ſay to all; therefore attend to the laſt words of a dying man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, See and conſider that the dayes of Grace have their laſt; the day long threatned is now come, when my preaching and your hearing can be continued no longer: ſo will it be with all your comforts and joyes, they will have an end. Oh! that you had ſeriouſly conſidered it, and prized thoſe opportunities of Grace you have had.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Let us heartily bleſs God for ſo many years freedom that we have had (eſpecially theſe laſt three years) in ſacred Ordinances: however thoſe opportunities that we have enjoyed be flighted by man, yet they muſt be
<pb facs="tcp:108768:4"/>reckoned for in the day of the Lord Jeſus. There have been many of late have ſtaved off Spiritual opportunities, and turned their backs upon Ordinances: the Lord be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to them; if they obtain not a pardon, woe be to their poor ſouls. I am as ſure and as certain to hear theſe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities mentioned in eternity with joy and ſorrow, as that ever the Sun did ſhine in the Firmament: acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge them thankfully; and eſpecially remember theſe laſt three years, about which time I have been with you, and have laboured in the publick ſervice of the Church of God amongſt you.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Depart not from the truths of God you have already received. I may ſay as St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth in the firſt of the <hi>Galatians,</hi> and <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>If any preach any other doctrine let him be accurſed.</hi> You muſt excuſe me for want of abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as others may have, yet hath it been my work (by the help of the holy Spirit) according to my power, to teach you out of holy Scripture thoſe things that concerns your everlaſting peace. Take heed of Antinomianiſme and Arminianiſme, never ceaſe a total dependance on the Grace of Chriſt, and a ſtrict reliance on him alone for life and ſalvation. This hath been my Doctrine from my firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning even until now, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.24.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, Oh! let Profeſſours ſtudy to honour God, <hi>Phillippians</hi> 4. I have walked amongſt you with a ſenſe upon my ſpirit. The Profeſſours in this City have much diſhonoured God. Oh! let there be zeal, ſincerity, love, humility and peace ſhining in the Profeſſours of this City. This is my counſel, now I am ready to depart from you, that your converſations may be ſuch as becometh the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, Own God in your Families, breed not up Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens
<pb facs="tcp:108768:4"/>in your Families to be lodged in Hell: if no Family Prayer, expect no Family Bleſſing: live as thoſe that knows there is a God, and would have God to be theirs; let not thy family be under a curſe, which it will be if thou calleſt not on the name of God. Haſt thou no care of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens and Servants ſouls, it is a ſign God hath no care of thine.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, Remember to ſanctifie the Lords Sabbath, breed not up thy Children in Sabbath breaking, if thou doeſt they will break thy heart. Haſt thou no care of Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath here, it is a thouſand to one whether thou ſhalt ever enjoy a Sabbath with God hereafter? Read that Text in the 58. of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and the two laſt verſes. If the Sabbath be the day of thy pleaſure, thy pain will be Gods pleaſure. If any come amongſt you and preach otherwiſe, I charge you receive not his doctrine; let God have the day called by his own name, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.8.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seventhly, Take heed of ſinking under any ſufferings; if for a good conſcience perſecutions may come, we know not how ſoon our Sins may deſerve it. Oh! ſink not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you that feel them, nor inſult not over thoſe that are under it. Old men, young men pray take notice of it; if you would damn your own ſouls, hate not them that would ſave theirs: remember what the voice from heaven ſaith, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.5. <hi>Saul, Saul, Why perſecutest thou me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Eighthly, Get all good from your Miniſter, and do all good to your Miniſter that God ſhall ſet over you; carry your ſelves towards him as becometh Chriſtians, with affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: whilſt he preacheth truth practiſe it. If any of you hinder me with affection, let not that hinder your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting by him; if he be one that you may profit by, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth reſpect from you.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:108768:5"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Ninthly, Study peace, Oh! live in peace, that is the counſel of my Text, <hi>and the God of love and peace will be with you.</hi> There is no queſtion but the Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts will be uſed rigorouſly, but be contented; I know that will be and is reported of them, that they are movers of Sedition, no friends to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> &amp;c. but they are miſtaken, for we are reſolved to live in peace with all men, and to ſit down contented under the hand of God. And it is my laſt counſel unto you, and the counſel of God in Scripture, that come what will come upon you, you ſtir not in thought, word, nor deed, againſt that lawful Power that God hath ſet over us.</p>
            <p>For my part the ſanctified experience that God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me of the unconſtancy of the world, cauſeth me not to be moved in the leaſt at this temptation. I bleſs my God for it, I have ſate down and counted my coſt already; and I aſſure you nothing but the wrath of the Almighty could have cauſed me to leave you; ſuch is my love to your ſouls and zeal to my duty. But whatſoever may be the cenſure of Authority upon us, I repeat it again, that there may be no miſtake; for it is like many may come this day to catch words, words out of my mouth to entrap me. I ſay, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Authority doth cenſure of us, I beg and beſeech you all, that you think of nothing, nor uſe any help to deliver your ſelves out of ſufferings, but Faith, Patience, and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. And I profeſs before you all, I have not ſpoken with, nor heard of any of this perſwaſion, but they are all againſt ever having any hand in any War, even thoſe who had a hand in the laſt; and therefore it is a horrible ſlander that is caſt upon the moſt peaceable Subjects that God and earthly Princes can have; pray Chriſtians let it appear ſo by your peaceable ſuffering. Conſider if thou ſuffer for
<pb facs="tcp:108768:5"/>Conſcience, thou muſt not revenge thy ſelf; if thou doeſt, thou loſeſt thy reward: Shew a ſpirit of Obedience in the exerciſe of Love and Patience. I do verily hope, and I am really perſwaded that I ſhall never hear of any Nonconformiſt that hath a hand in any Riſing or Sedition whatſoever. This is my ninth counſel, <hi>Study peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Tenthly, Be not troubled at thoſe reproaches that the enimies of God may caſt upon you, taking advantage at Gods diſappointment of our hopes and providence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us. It is very likely many of you may hear them ſay, what is become of your precious Preacher now you ſo much boaſted of? where is your godly brave gifted man? where will you go next? how will you diſpoſe of your ſelves? Now I hope you that have been my hearers, and profeſſors ſo long, have an anſwer ready to ſhame them, and am ſorry if thou haſt not, ſaying, Although I have loſt my earthly Teacher, yet I have an heavenly Teacher; I have a God to go to, which you cannot take from me. Shew that thou carrieſt grace in thy heart, and thy God is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. They do but upbraid thee with their own miſery, curſe, and wrath, when they ask thee what is become of ſuch a one. Brethren, would we have debaucht our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, had we not as fair an opportunity as other men to have continued; thou that carrieſt a good Conſcience and haſt an intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt, what needſt thou care what man can do to thee; look upon thy reward and comfort thou ſhalt one day have, and look upon thy ſelf with a great deal of holy comfort and confidence, and thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in a ſerious manner ſmile at their folly and madneſs, how they ſport themſelves in the loſs of that light that might bring them to heaven.</p>
            <p>I confeſs it is a great reproach and a great affliction; it
<pb facs="tcp:108768:6"/>made <hi>David</hi> cry out, <hi>Lord, let me not be confounded.</hi> When the enemy ſaid, <hi>Where is now your God.</hi> Many in like manner now cry out, where is now your God! Heretofore you ſaid there was a ſtream of Providence did follow Holineſs, but now where is it? doth God like this preciſeneſs and <hi>extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</hi> Praying, and long Preaching? no, God likes a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal kinde of ſerving him beſt, ſuch as is according to the Church, and as it was in our fore-fathers dayes; he owns it, favours it, and ſmiles upon it. Come, come, Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is various, <hi>David</hi> ſtaggers at it, till he comes to weigh the caſe in the ballance of the Sanctuary; be not caſt down at theſe reproaches, either thou haſt got good by the Ordinances or not; if not, thou art in a ſad conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: if thou haſt, what needeſt thou care for the reproach of man, what need a man care to be upbraided of having his Cup-board plundered when his Treaſure was ſafe in a ſurer place. Chriſtian thy treaſure is in heaven, thieves cannot there break through and ſteal. Conſider, this is not a place where things goes right, it will go right in another day; now thou liveſt amongſt Drunkards and prophane perſons, there is no room for ſuch in heaven; look upon things now as it will go then, and let thoſe words of the Judge ſtick cloſe to thy heart; <hi>He that is aſhamed of me, and of my word, in this adulterous and ſinful generation, of him ſhall the Son of man be aſhamed when he comes in the glory of his Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Twelfthly, Learn how to behave your ſelves well in the day of <hi>Jacobs</hi> troubles; though we are all now in peace, bleſſed be God for it, yet we know not what may befall us ere we come to dye, when I ſhall not be here to adviſe you: and ſuppoſing this may be your cafe, and wiſhing you well, even as my own ſoul, I am bold to adviſe you how you
<pb facs="tcp:108768:6"/>ſhall behave your ſelves when it comes. Out of love to your ſouls I adviſe you what to do in the day of <hi>Jacobs</hi> troubles.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, have the mark of mourners on your foreheads, let me beg it of you, if you have not that mark on you in the day of <hi>Jacobs</hi> troubles, without doubt the Devils black mark will be found on you at the laſt day. In <hi>Ezekiel 9. v.</hi> 4.5. all that had not this mark on them were the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons deſtinated to deſtruction. When the overflowing ſcourge comes, when the deſtroying Angel goeth upon his circuit, he is not to ſpare man, woman, nor childe; but thoſe that had this mark upon them, even thoſe that cried out for the abominations done in the land. Read that text. Now mark the difference that God and the world puts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch mourners in <hi>Sion;</hi> God puts a mark of preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon ſuch as the world puts a mark of deſtruction; ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, humorſome, keeping a whining, faſting, and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: behave your ſelves well in the day of <hi>Jacobs</hi> trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, get the mark of mourners on your foreheads, let not God ſee that you are a careleſs people; let not God that ſees this Congregation, this great number of people have cauſe to ſay that you are a careleſs company; care not for your own ſins, nor for the ſins of others; care not for the wrath of God, though gray hairs be here and there upon us, you know it not; care not for the Churches miſery, though <hi>Jacob</hi> be under the hatches, and the Church like to be grownd to powder, thou canſt trudge about the world and endeavour to preſerve thy Eſtate, but careſt not for the wrath of God, nor the miſeries of the Church: Thou art not one of thoſe perſons that behaveſt thy ſelf well in the day of <hi>Jacobs</hi> troubles. I tell thee, if the ſins of a Nation be nothing to thee, the judgements of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:108768:7"/>ſhall be ſomething to thee. Remember that a meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Jeſus Chriſt, a poor dying worm, who is juſt now leaving you, told you thus much; that if the ungodlineſs, prophaneneſs, ſenſuality, blaſphemy, and atheiſme of a Nation be nothing to thee, then the judgements of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be ſomething to thee. Either mourn for ſin, or mourn for woe and ſorrow. Oh! do you mourn for the wickedneſs that is done in this Land, though ſinners make ſport of it, and pleaſe themſelves in it, and look upon it as part of their glory that they can go to Hell quietly; let me beg it of you all, and leave it as my counſel with you, to get the mark of mourners on your foreheads; let it appear that the Angel may take notice of thee, and mark thee when the overflowing ſcourge ſhall paſs through the land. Really there is hypocriſie in Profeſſors on both hands, in times of the Churches proſperity, and in times of the Churches adverſity: the Devil may tell thee that thou art ſincere, though thou takeſt no notice of the Churches trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, nor mourneſt for it; be not deceived, thy heart is not right in the ſight of God if thou careſt not what becomes of his Church; thou haſt had a hand in their ſins, have a hand in their ſufferings. Thou haſt helpt to bring ſorrow to the Church by reaſon of thy ſin, Oh bring tears of godly ſorrow to help to quench the flame that ſinne hath kindled!</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, would you behave your ſelves well in the time of <hi>Jacobs</hi> troubles, keep your ſelves pure from the reigning ſins of the times wherein you live. I ſpeak not of any particular time, but when God is angry with his Church, let it be now, be it when it will, it then becomes Chriſtians to keep themſelves pure from the ſins of thoſe times.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:108768:7"/>
            <p> In <hi>Revel.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 4. hearken to that text of Scripture, thou carnal, complying, temporizing, and time-ſerving Profeſſour <hi>I heard a voice from heaven ſaying, Come out of her my people, and be not partakers of her ſin, leſt you are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of her plagues.</hi> When mens ſins are filling apace, when the Ephah is near full, keep thy ſelf pure from the ſins of the times, leſt thou be made partaker of the plagues of the times. Conſider what are the ſins of ſuch times, if there be prophaneneſs, ſuperſtition, impiety, malice againſt Religion, ſenſuality, impenitency, and ſee little elſe but wickedneſs of this dye and nature, touch you not one of them, keep your ſelves pure. I am giving you counſel as for my own life, if I were dying on my ſick bed, as God knows how ſoon I may, according to the meaſure that God hath given me of his free Grace, I could not give you better counſel. Oh that I could deliver it with that authority that I ought. Purity is a condition of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18. <hi>He will be to you a Father, and you ſhall be to him Sons and Daughters,</hi> if you will come out from ſuch uncleanneſſes. A word to the wiſe is enough, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as God furniſheth you with his Spirit, learn to behave your ſelves well in the day of <hi>Jacobs</hi> troubles, keep your ſelves pure from the ſins of the times.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Feel the ſorrow of the Church; if the Church be nothing to thee, Chriſt is nothing to thee; and if Chriſt be nothing to thee, thou art an enemy to Chriſt; and thou mayeſt profeſs thou beleeveſt in Chriſt, and hopes to be ſaved by Chriſt; but if the Church be nothing to thee, thou art but a dead Member, a wooden Leg, a glaſs Eye, an artificial Tooth. You muſt be either friends or foes to Chriſt; if friends, then friends to his Church; if thou doeſt not gather with him, thou ſcattereſt; and if thou
<pb facs="tcp:108768:8"/>takes not a common intereſt with the Church of God, thou art but a falſe friend to Chriſt: if thou doſt not feel the Churches pain, thou haſt none of the Churches Spirit: if a finger or a toe ſuffer, the whole body is ſenſible. Thou haſt none of the Spirit of Chriſt, if thou doeſt not feel the ſorrows of the Church. <hi>Woe be to thoſe that dwell at eaſe in Sion;</hi> very few great men are like good <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> who was of the Kings Court, and in great favour with him, and ailed nothing, yet his heart was full of ſorrow for the Church of God; inſomuch that the King ſaw by his countenance that he was troubled; and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> made uſe of the opportunity, and reſted not till he had accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed his deſign for the Houſe of God. Men that have a great eſtate, and in great places, many times are the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt enemies to the Church of God; and they are ready to forſake Chriſt, like the rich young man in the Goſpel, which you may read at your leaſure.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Amos</hi> 6. <hi>ver.</hi> 6. read your doom there, (if the Devil do poſſeſs ſome of you with prejudice, I profeſs ſeriouſly Brethren, it is in love to your ſouls I ſpeak) read that 6. <hi>verſe</hi> of the 6. of <hi>Amos,</hi> poor <hi>Joſeph</hi> lay by the heels, the Irons entered into his ſoul: <hi>But thoſe that took their pleaſure and was not ſorry for the affliction of Joſeph, ſhould go into captivity with the firſt that went into captivity.</hi> The Church hath a flood of perſecution, and mouths full of the venom of the old Serpent is ſpit out after them; yet the Church is kept ſafe. In the 25. of <hi>Matthew</hi> you have three famous parables; of the ten Virgins, of the Talents, of the Sheep and Goats; there you may ſee that the trial of the laſt day is according to the ſimpathizing with the Church. Do but conſider it ſeriouſly, it is according as thou haſt ſympathized with the Church that thy tryal will
<pb facs="tcp:108768:8"/>then be. You ſaw me in my Members, in my poor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Members, you never looked after them; <hi>and inaſmuch as you did it not to one of the leaſt of theſe, you did it not to me. Then ſhall they go into everlaſting pains, but the righteous into life eternal.</hi> Pray remember this, there will be a day of judgement, and the Scripture is the rule by which all muſt be tryed that lives under it. The love of the Brethren is the mark by which we ſhall be judged at the laſt day, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.14. <hi>We know that we are paſſed from death to life, becauſe we love the Brethren.</hi> Thoſe that are ſpiritual Brethren, that have God for their Father, Jeſus Chriſt for their elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, new Jeruſalem that is above for their Mother, ought ſo to love one another, as the Apoſtle ſaith in that 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>That they ought to lay down their lives for each other.</hi> If God doth call for thy Eſtate, thy Life, thy Hearts Blood to be ſacrificed for him, thou oughteſt to do it. Brethren, amongſt other Arguments, to ſway with a true Son of the Church, this ſhould be one; what, ſhall I turn upon the Church of God now in affliction? what a ſtumbling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>block and cauſe of offence will it be to my weak Brother. Brethren, when God ſeems to call upon you, ſaying, Who is on the Lords ſide, and who is not? you are to love the Church ſo, as if your lives did lie at ſtake to part with it; every member ſhould endeavour the preſervation of the whole.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, wouldſt thou behave thy ſelf well in the day of <hi>Jacobs</hi> troubles, give God no reſt day nor night till he have mercy on his people; until he take his rod from the back of the righteous; until he make his Church a triumph and rejoycing over the whole earth.</p>
            <p>Prayers and tears are the Churches weapons, uſe no other, for thoſe are the weapons that will fell tall and
<pb facs="tcp:108768:9"/>ſtately Cedars; thoſe be the weapons that will ſcatter Kingdoms. It is ſaid of a Queen of the Scots, that ſhe was more afraid of <hi>John Knox,</hi> then of an Army of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thouſand men; ſuch was his prevalency in Prayer. Are you living men or not, do you breath or not? if you are ſpiritually alive, and living Members of the Church of Chriſt, you cannot but lay cloſe ſiege at the Throne of Grace in its behalf. Doſt thou pray to God, and canſt thou pray and forget the Iſrael of God? Haſt thou a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary care that thy own ſoul ſhall be ſaved, and forgets the Church of God in miſery, never putting up a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious petition for Gods Iſrael, nor mindeſt the afflictions of <hi>Joſeph.</hi> Oh! give God no reſt day nor night until he hath mercy on Sion. This is a ſucceſsful war that you are commanded and encouraged unto in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62. <hi>ver.</hi> 6, 7. <hi>I have ſet watch-men upon thy walls, O Jeruſalem, that ſhall never hold their peace day nor night, until he eſtabliſh Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and make it the praiſe of the whole earth: Ye that make mention of the Lord keep not ſilence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh the Lord increaſe the number of ſuch perſons! Oh! that you that are real Members of the Church would ſtand upon the walls and give God no reſt day nor night until he hath eſtabliſhed <hi>Sion,</hi> and made <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the praiſe of the earth, Oh! bleſs God for the ſucceſs of Prayer, when poor weak impotent craſie prayers engageth All-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency and Omnipotency to do this. Read <hi>Pſalm</hi> 137. and the 6. firſt verſes, <hi>By the Rivers of Babylon we ſate down, yea, we wept when we remembred thee, O Zion, we hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our harps upon the willows in the midſt thereof;</hi> it was no time to hear the ſound of them, we were not ſo merry. <hi>They that waſted us required of us mirth, ſaying, Sing us one of the Songs of Zion.</hi> Come, let us have ſome of your zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb facs="tcp:108768:9"/>mirth. Come let us hear you now pray in the Spirit, and preach <hi>ex tempore;</hi> then it becomes us to hang our harps on the willows, and ſay, <hi>How ſhall we ſing the Lords Song in a ſtrange Land.</hi> Now we have loſt our Ordinances, and are given up to the hands of Heathens that reigns over us. <hi>If I forget thee, O Jeruſalem, let my right hand forget her cunning: If I do not remember thee, let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth, if I prefer not Jeruſalem above my chief joy.</hi> Oh pathetical expreſſion, he did not ſhrink from the Church of God; but ſee with what affection he ſpeaks, <hi>If I forget thee,</hi> &amp;c. I muſt forget that which I am uſed to do, <hi>If I prefer not Jeruſalem above my chief joy.</hi> Oh Brethren, get this ſpirit of affection towards the Church. Really, Brethren, I am afraid few of you are real Members of the Church? were you, you would be more importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate at the Throne of Grace for the Churches eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: ſee what you may do by importunity in that 18. Chapter of <hi>Luke.</hi> from the firſt verſe to the 8. Brethren, you muſt pardon me becauſe it is my laſt, and although I am ſo long a taking leave of you, yet will it be no obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction unto you in your journey, but a furtherance. See what an encouragement there is in that 18. of <hi>Luke, And he ſpake a parable unto them, to this end, that men ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to pray, and not to faint.</hi> Oh! faint not in your pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for if the unjuſt judge that feared not God, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded man, yet was wrought upon to avenge the poor widow becauſe of her importunity; <hi>and ſhall not God avenge his own Elect that cries day and night to him; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he bear long? I tell you, he will avenge them ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily.</hi> The cloud over the Church may be ſo thick, and the eſtate of the Church ſo deſperate, that when the Son of Man comes, he ſhall hardly finde faith on the earth. Do
<pb facs="tcp:108768:10"/>you think that God will not hear his own Elect, but ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their enemies to make ſuch deep furrows over them; although he do ſeem long to thy carnal ſenſe, yet when his time is come, he will come and not tarry: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bear a ſenſe upon thy ſpirit of the Churches miſery, for he that can be quiet in the Churches miſery, hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved himſelf from the Churches light and ſociety; he hath caſhier'd himſelf out of the myſtical Body, however he may ſeem to be in outward ſociety. Oh! therefore feel and ſimpathize with the Church in her miſery. I only ask thee one queſtion, Art thou content to have no part in the happineſs of the Church hereafter? if thou ſeparateſt thy ſelf from the Church Militant, I tell thee, in the name of my Lord and Maſter, thou ſhalt be ſeparated from the Church Triumphant hereafter. Wouldſt thou ſtand at the right hand of the Head of the Church, and be owned as a Member, and be glorified for ever with the Church? why, then here feel the Churches ſorrow, and cry mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God that he will ariſe and have mercy on Sion.</p>
            <p>But if thou doeſt not here feel the Churches miſery, nor cry to God for deliverance, thou muſt be ſeparated from the Church hereafter. And thus have I done with this general counſel, learn to behave your ſelves well in the day of <hi>Jacobs</hi> troubles, in four particulars; Get the mark of mourners on your foreheads. Keep your ſelves pure from the reigning ſins of the times. Feel the ſorrows of the Church. And cry mightily unto God that he would have mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> I now come to the 13 and laſt general counſel that I have to leave with you, and that is, Be you all truly wiſe: Once more I ſay, my laſt general counſel unto you is, O be you all truly wiſe. It is not an outward wiſdom I would coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel
<pb facs="tcp:108768:10"/>you to, but it is a ſpiritual wiſdom, a true wiſdom: Oh learn it, it will do you good to all eternity. Once more hearken to a few counſels from your departing friend, which contains the ſubſtance of the greateſt wiſdom in the world, and I am heartily willing to leave them with you as my farewel; be truly wiſe, take good counſel in theſe following particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, View truth, loſe not true wiſdom, let not the god of this world blinde thine eyes any longer; thou that haſt a dark head here, and doeſt not ſee the ſaving truth, thou mayeſt be blinde for ever hereafter. Do not loſe the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Goſpel, the ſight of Divine Beauty, this is but a world of ſhadows, ſtocks, and ſtraws, and butter-flies. Oh get a ſight of the world to come, think, read, hear, meditate, that thou mayeſt behold the beauty of Truth; be much in hearing, be much in reading, read good Books, meditate on them; the leſs opportunity the ear hath, the more op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity the eye ſhould have: darkneſs is the Devils kingdom, he is the prince of darkneſs, and deeds of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are done in the Devils kingdom; get out of it into the glorious Goſpel of Light; view Truth and ſtudy it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Follow the light of it, firſt ſee it, then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it; people are apt to think they are in a good way when they are in a bad: when you view Truth and have ſeen Divine Beauty, then follow light, or elſe turn ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, that Infiniteneſs it ſelf cannot get thee out of it. If thou diſobeyeſt Conſcience, thou runneſt upon the point of the ſword; Conſcience is that which is a diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; bread is bread, and grain is grain, but the goodneſs of it is better diſtinguiſhed by being brought to the light. Sin is ſin, but bring it to the light of Conſcience, it is clearer diſcerned; thou that art a drunkard againſt thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb facs="tcp:108768:11"/>a ſwearer, a profaner of the Lords Day, a reviler of his people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and doſt it againſt the light of thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, what canſt thou ſay for thy ſelf at that day of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count when this Book ſhall be laid open among the reſt, and all thy deeds of darkneſs diſcovered? Thou that in matters of Religious Worſhip doeſt any thing againſt thy conſcience, runneſt upon inavoidable miſery and woe, and thou ſhalt finde bitterneſs in the end.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Live in the practiſe of ſelf-deniel, Oh take heed of the Fleſh and the Devil; ſo much as thou art ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by theſe thine enemies, ſo far thou ſetteſt thy ſelf from the enjoyment of God; for if ſelf-pleaſing be not counted by thee to be thine enemy, and ſelf-denial thy friend, thou art out of the convoy of God; what then will be thy end? Live crucifying of thy fleſh, or thou ſhalt be crucified by it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, Live in the ſight of, and dependance on the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, live in the ſight thereof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually; ſo long as thou art out of the ſight of God, ſo long thou art open to all dangers. Depend upon the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for giving, upon the Son for purchaſing, upon the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt for conveighing all good unto thee; expreſs thy dependance by thy earneſt prayers to God for all good, tugging and ſtriving for thy life; expreſs thy dependance by a hanging and relying faith upon thy Saviour, reſiſting all temptations, reſolve to live in the ſight of, and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on Father, Son, and Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, Live in a good air, keep good company; a ſoul that is in evil company is in Hell, whilſt amongſt them, or elſe will go to Hell with them. There is nothing more healthful to the body then to live in a good aire; a bad air deſtroyes the health, ſo doth bad company deſtroy the ſoul; reſiſt temptations, thou muſt part with God or with
<pb facs="tcp:108768:11"/>evil company; therefore forſake bad company, reſiſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations at firſt riſing: if thou doſt not watch the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of temptations to ſin, all thy vows and promiſes will vaniſh as dew before the Sun.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, Exchange temporal joyes for eternal, be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of it, the world will leave you this garment, the covering of it will fade; therefore whilſt the colour is any thing good, get a better and more enduring; part with the worlds contents for ſpiritual joyes: this you are to do by daily mortification, diligent edification; and be ſure to reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy ſincerity towards God, make good <hi>friends of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Mammon; that when you fail, they may receive you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to everlaſting habitations, Luke</hi> 16. Make friends with your eſtate, lay it out upon chriſts poor Members; really the world is going away apace, Heaven and Earth is chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and waxeth old, there are joyes everlaſting: Oh then exchange temporal joyes for eternal.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seventhly, Fill thy ſelf with religious pleaſures, expect and overlook its cares; if thou wouldeſt be truly wiſe do this, the heart muſt have its joy either temporal or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual; would you trample over the world, then <hi>rejoyce in the Lord: and again I ſay, rejoyce.</hi> Oh be truly wiſe, let God, Heaven, and the Holy Spirit continually fill thy ſoul with religious joyes, ſweetneſs, and beauty which will baniſh thy cares and dangers; if thou art religious expect troubles, but overlook them and caſt thine eyes upon that joy that is in thy ſoul, that thou art out of the reach of Satan and his inſtruments, being under the ſafe conduct of Omnipotency, who will undoubtedly bring thee ſafe through all to himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Eighthly, If thou loveſt life, let death dwell in thy heart, God knows how ſoon we may all dye: now I am
<pb facs="tcp:108768:12"/>going away and am not to ſpeak any more unto you, except God finde out a way beyond our expectation; I would therefore leave that counſel that may do you moſt good, and make you truly wiſe. Remember to have death alwayes before your eyes, and provide for it; there are none wiſe but thoſe, and all ſuch are truly wiſe that keeps death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes: moſt people in the world are looking the other way, they are providing for long life, not for their death. Put your hearts into a ſerious meditation of death, and ſeriouſly conſider, that although troubles here comes thick upon you, and temptations daily aſſault you, death when it comes will put you out of the reach thereof, and make you happy for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Ninthly, Conform ſolemnly to the terms of ſalvation, to wit, impartial dependance and affiance upon the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: if ever thou wouldſt be truly wiſe here, and eternally happy hereafter, do this; until thou haſt done this, thou wilt never be happy: depend wholly on Chriſt, exerciſing faith upon Jeſus Chriſt alone for life and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> And laſtly, Be reſolved never to depart from faith and holineſs, let the iſſue and event be what it will, never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from it; faith and holineſs are the pillars that fail not, heaven and earth ſhall fail us e're theſe ſhall go away; therefore if God doth ſcourge thee and chaſtiſe thee, keep faſt faith and holineſs: whatever would keep thee from faith and holineſs is not of God; live therefore in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of it here, and thou ſhalt live in the reward of it for ever hereafter. Pray conſider theſe ten things and dwell upon them, take my laſt counſel, be truly wiſe: Oh that they may ſtick upon your hearts and dwell there until your hearts come to dwell with God for ever; which I wiſh
<pb facs="tcp:108768:12"/>from my ſoul may be your portion.</p>
            <p>Give me leave to take my leave of you, now I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to give you the whole counſel of God, and to nurſe you up, that you may grow ſtronger and ſtronger thereby. My time approacheth that I muſt leave you, ſtay but until I bid you farewel, and then we will part here, and I hope to meet you again at our journeyes end, where we will rejoyce in <hi>the Lord our righteouſneſſe,</hi> and our <hi>joy ſhall no man take from us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The providence of God brought me hither at firſt in a way, and by a means which many of you were pleaſed to acknowledge had much of the hand of God in it. I was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinated from all eternity to be your Miniſter: For you was I ordained, you have I loved, you have I taught, with you have I lived, and with you could I have continued; nothing but the keeping of a good conſcience could have hindered it on my part. I came not hither on my own head, neither do I go away upon a whimſie of my own making: Great proffers of preferment formerly moved me not, but the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the Almighty now makes me afraid; my heart could not be ſtrong, nor my hands endure in the day of the Lord, ſhould I againſt my conſcience have continued amongſt you. This I can ſay, Brethren, in the preſence of the Lord (that although in much weakneſs and infirmity, and much ſlightneſs and little ſeriouſneſs) I have laboured amongſt you to the ſalvation of your ſouls, for which I have pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and waited for.</p>
            <p>I deſire this day to humble my ſelf before God and you, and beg the mercy of God in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt for all my miſcarriages, and neglects, and failings amongſt you, for the want of ſo good an example as I ſhould have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, that I have not melted in pitty and compaſſion
<pb facs="tcp:108768:13"/>over your ſouls, nor have been ſo zealous in private admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition as I ſhould; yet let the good you have ſeen and heard of me abide with you; let the ſpiritual rules and motives you have abundantly heard dwell richly in you; take heed of hypocriſie, be ſincere, watch and examine your hearts, look into eternity, and live by faith upon Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I heartily bleſs God for my continuance hitherto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, for your willing reception of me, for all your courteſies and civil deportments towards me, for all your chearful and hearty hearing the word of God by me prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; and moſt of all, I bleſs God for any good that any of you have received by me. I thank you for all the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments of my requeſts, I thank every particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that hath done me any good, the Lord reward them; I have endeavoured to live affectionately in the midſt of you: and pray if any perſon have any thing againſt me, I deſire to make it known unto me before my departure, and I will give him ſatisfaction; let no man lay any thing to my charge when I am gone, that will not make it known before I go.</p>
            <p>I thank you all for your deſire of me to ſtay, the Lord knows how loath I am to leave you, might I conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue amongſt you with a good conſcience. Oh! that the Sermons you have heard of me may be practiſed; we ſhall one day meet at the bar of Chriſt, and then I wiſh I may not be a witneſs againſt any ſoul here preſent.</p>
            <p>If any of you have been my ſpiritual children, do ſo much in requital as to pray for your ſpiritual Father; if I have been only a waterer and no planter, yet let me reap the fruits of your Prayers, and let my name live in your private prayers when it is dead in publick; ſend tokens for me to
<pb facs="tcp:108768:13"/>Heaven, when you ſhall ſee my face no more on earth; let us meet at the Throne of Grace, though we ſhall not meet in this houſe no more: let your Prayers to Almighty God for me be continued, that my whole ſoul and body may be ever preſent as a living ſacrifice unto God, holy and accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in his ſight; that I may live onely to Jeſus; that he would uſe me ſo as is beſt to his own glory, in doing and ſuffering, and enable me to be faithful to what he hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me to; and that himſelf would be my <hi>exceeding great reward;</hi> and that he would not deny himſelf unto me, for whom I have deſired to have been ſtripped of all things.</p>
            <p>Neither ſhall your prayers be without the anſwer of mine; the Road where I travel on, the Bed that I lie on, the Room that I ſhall lie in, ſhall teſtifie how much I bear you, that have been my hearers, in my boſom.</p>
            <p>And my prayers continually ſhall be for you that you may fare well, <hi>and the God of love and peace be with you;</hi> that ſhall aſcend from my heart and lips when you are aſleep, at work, ſtanding, or ſitting in your Shops, or abroad in the Fields.</p>
            <p>Oh may you fare well in all Eſtates, in the day of your temptations and trials, <hi>and the God of love and peace be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh! may you fare well in the dayes of your ſorrows and afflictions, <hi>and the God of love and peace be with you</hi> in the fire, and in the water, that you may come out ſeven times refined, and give you the garment of praiſe for the ſpirit of heavineſs.</p>
            <p>May you fare well in your joyes and comforts, <hi>and the God of love and peace be with you,</hi> and bring you to his right hand, <hi>where are joyes unſpeakable, and pleaſures for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May you fare well in your Shops, and in your Fields, at Sea, and aſhore, in your going out, and in your coming in,
<pb facs="tcp:108768:14"/>ſhall be the hearty prayers of your dying friend.</p>
            <p>May you be bleſſed in your basket, and in your ſtore, and in all things you put your hands unto, <hi>and the God of love and peace be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May you be bleſſed in your Yoak-fellows, in your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Servants, in your Miniſters, and all your relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>and the God of love and peace be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May you be bleſſed in the exerciſes of your graces and duties, and Ordinances, <hi>and the God of love and peace be with you,</hi> and make them eaſie, fruitful, and delightful.</p>
            <p>May you fare well in the hour of death, <hi>the God of love and peace</hi> then ſpeak peace unto you, and ſhew his recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled face unto you in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>May you fare well at the great day of Judgement, <hi>and the God of love and peace</hi> then ſet you at his right hand, ſmile upon you, acquit and diſſolve you.</p>
            <p>May you fare well in the day of eternity, <hi>and the God of love and peace</hi> then lead you to the fountain of living wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to the enjoyment of himſelf, that ſorrow and ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may then flie away, that you may live in praiſing and ſinging Hallelujah in the Quire of Angels to all eternity.</p>
            <p>May none of you here preſent know what Hell means, ſo as to feel the Torments thereof; but that you may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Kingdom of Heaven, where <hi>the God of love and peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May mine enemies do well, though I know but of few, except thoſe who were once my friends; thoſe that are, <hi>the God of love and peace be with them,</hi> and bleſs them for ever. Thoſe that have ſpoken ill of me, the good will of him that dwelt in the Buſh be with them, and pardon all their ſins, enrich them with Grace, and bring them to his heavenly Kingdom: I do from my ſoul forgive them, and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:108768:14"/>deſire of God that I may know what it is to live in their company to all eternity, whoſe favour here I could not gain. This I can ſay, there is none I have more heartily loved then my enemies, to do good for evil; to paſs by provocations hath been my endeavour: let them enjoy the love of God, whoſe company here I could not enjoy.</p>
            <p>May my friends be rewarded, let them be reaping in the day of eternity, for every good thought, word, and work towards me, however ſo unworthy, ſeeing it was done in the name of a Prophet, <hi>let them receive a Prophets reward;</hi> the upper and the nether ſprings be their portion, all the graces and priviledges of the Goſpel be beſtowed on them, and the God of Grace and Glory be with them.</p>
            <p>I cannot ſay more, the Sun is even down, my civil life is near an end, my ſtrength is almoſt ſpent, but the remainder ſhall be ſpent for your good.</p>
            <p>Let all the treaſures of Divine Love be the reward of all thoſe who have ſhewed love unto me.</p>
            <p>May every particular Family in this place be bleſſed. Let every Houſe wherein I have been, and every perſon therein be bleſſed; eſpecially thoſe Families wherein I have been particularly engaged: Let every one of them be the heir of Temporal, Spiritual, and Eternal Glory, the Lord binde up their ſouls in the bundle of Life.</p>
            <p>Now as to my Adminiſtrations.</p>
            <p>Farewel Sermons, and farewel Sabbaths, farewel Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and farewel Exhortations, farewel this Houſe, and farewel this Seat for ever, farewel my Preaching, farewel your Hearing, and farewel your Faces in this place, and farewel this world, when we ſhall arrive at eternity, both old and young.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:108768:15"/>
            <p>My Brethren and Siſters all farewel, and God give us himſelf, which is all in all. And now to conclude with the farewel in my Text, and ſo to commend you all to God by Prayer, which is my laſt work.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally my Brethren, farewel: Be perfect, be ye of one minde, be of good comfort, live in peace, and the God of love and peace be with you all. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:108768:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Edward Hancock's <hi>Prayer before his Farewel Sermon, at St.</hi> PHILIPS, <hi>in</hi> Briſtol, Auguſt 24. 1662.</head>
            <p>Holy Lord God, Thou who art the Spring of Being, the Root of the World, the Foundation of all, the Centre of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls, unto thee ſhall all Fleſh come.</p>
            <p>Souls muſt have vent, they have not a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent happineſs at home to live upon, they muſt look out and ſeek abroad; and it is vanity to give vent to the Soul any way, except up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. Prayer is the greateſt vent and hearts eaſe in all the world unto immortal Souls: Lord at this time lift up our Hearts by Prayer unto thee in and through the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>O Lord, we are unworthy to come into thy preſence at this time; truly we do confeſs it, being conſidered in our ſtate of Nature; Oh
<pb facs="tcp:108768:16"/>how were we by the tranſgreſſion of our firſt Parents born Children of Wrath and Heirs of eternal Damnation; and our whole Life ever ſince hath been a life of Sin and actual Rebellion againſt thy Majeſty. Alas, we are unworthy to pour out our deſires before thee, we are Dogs, yet truth Lord, the Dogs may eat of the crumbs that fall from thy Table. O Lord, are there ſo many now about thy Houſe, and ſhall none of them be filled with good things that they be not ſent empty away. O Lord, thou art a bountiful Houſe-keeper, that deals out a large deal of ſpiritual gifts for every poor ſoul that is poor and hungry, and empty in his own apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Bleſſed are the poor in ſpirit, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Thou haſt bid us open our mouths wide, and thou wilt fill them; Oh open our mouths abroad, our hearts do thou open at this time that they may be filled.</p>
            <p>O Lord, time would fail us, ſtrength would fail us, and memory would fail us, to make a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular recapitulation of all our Sins and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions committed againſt thee: We carry bad hearts about us, hearts that are never weary of offending a good God, that waits that he
<pb facs="tcp:108768:16"/>may be gracious. O Lord, we would fain lay open the deſires of our ſouls before thee, it is pardoning mercy and healing mercy we would beg of thee, for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake pardon all our Sins original and actual, and waſh our ſouls in that <hi>fountain opened for the houſe of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah and Jeruſalem, for ſin and for uncleanneſs.</hi> Change our natures, chain up our corruptions; Oh ſubdue our iniquities, and give us thy Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>For by nature we are prone to all wickedneſs, we have not a rag to cover our nakedneſs; Lord cover us with the Robes of Chriſts Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. O Lord we pray thee bring us into the bond of the Covenant, ſanctifie our hearts and lives for ever, to the honour of thy great Name. Take this opportunity of working up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, deal with us mightily by thy Spirit, who knows what a day may bring forth? we know not how ſoon death may beat up our quarters and ſtorm our caſtles, the next meſſenger that knocks may be the meſſenger of Death; let us therefore be ſerious, and betake our ſelves to ſoul concernments. Let us conſider Sabbaths were not made for nought, to pleaſe an itching
<pb facs="tcp:108768:17"/>ear, or unruly fancy; but to ſave our ſouls.</p>
            <p>O Lord make us diligent and careful at this time to receive ſpiritual good from thee. Put us into thy Covenant, carry us ſafe through this world, bring us out of a natural condition, give ſincerity to ſouls that groan under hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; give us a heart to know thee <hi>the Lord our Righteouſneſſe,</hi> do ſaving good to us this day; our laſt dayes are not the leaſt but of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt concernment; the deſires of our ſouls unto thy Majeſty is, that it may go well with us at thoſe two laſt great dayes of Death and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. O that our dying dayes and dooms dayes may be delightful and pleaſant dayes to us!</p>
            <p>We are but ſeeming Actors in a play in this world, we are but a ſhadow, how ſoon are we gone, and our Habitations ſhall ſee us no more.</p>
            <p>O Eternity, Eternity, Eternity, that our ſouls muſt ſhortly launch into a vaſt ocean; where there is a great account to be given how we have behaved our ſelves in this life: Oh grant that we may ſo provide for that day, that
<pb facs="tcp:108768:17"/>we may render our account with joy, and not with grief.</p>
            <p>O <hi>Lord to whom ſhall we go, thou haſt the words of eternal life;</hi> make us (like thy ſelf) partakers of thy Divine Nature, deliver us into the mould of thy word; thou knoweſt the condition of us, let thy Word reach us all. Oh Lord run up thy Sword to the Hilt in the hearts of all impenitent Sinners, make thy Word ſharper then a two-edged Sword.</p>
            <p>O Lord thou haſt done good by thy ſervants in their departing from us, do good at this time amongſt us: Oh let thy ſtrength be put forth to the conviction, humiliation, enlightning, and converting of many a Soul this day. Our ſtrength is but ſmall, we cannot be ſo importunate with thee as our hearts doth deſire; thou knoweſt our ſtate and wants, do exceedingly for us above and beyond what we are able to ask or think.</p>
            <p>O Lord, thou art willing to do us good, thou profeſſeſt thou takeſt no pleaſure in the death of a Sinner; what then ſhould hinder in all the world, but a ſecret unwillingneſs in our hearts to come over to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: For his ſake, by this laſt throw of the Adminiſtration of
<pb facs="tcp:108768:18"/>thy Grace, let ſome poor fouls that ſticks and ſtayes long in the place of bringing forth, be born to Jeſus Chriſt at this time. Although this be the laſt Sermon (in an ordinary way) that ever thy unworthy ſervant is like to preach in this Congregation, let it be a quickning Sermon, an effectual Ordinance, ſanctified by thy Spirit, to convert many and many a Soul: work like a God, work like thy own ſelf; let the power of the Lord be ſeen in the weakneſs of thy Servant.</p>
            <p>Lord ſhew mercy unto all, carry on thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Churches deſign, let not the gates of Hell prevail; <hi>Let not the rod of the wicked alwayes reſt upon the back of the righteous;</hi> ſtand by thine in this hour of temptation: though they be but weak in grace, yet they have a ſtrong God; O ſupport them, and let the name of the Lord be great in the midft of them.</p>
            <p>In much mercy look on theſe ſinful Nations; Oh bleſs our Sovereign Lord the King in his perſon, and in his Relations; thou that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt all things, doth know, that it is the deſire of our ſouls, that thou wouldeſt bleſs him with a competency of Spiritual, Temporal, and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Glory.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:108768:18"/>
            <p> Oh make him a King after thy own heart, we are reſolved to wait on thee; who knoweth what a day may bring forth? what a God can do to the terrour and aſtoniſhment of all his enemies? Let them ſee that <hi>the Kings heart is in the hand of the Lord, and he can turn it as pleaſeth him:</hi> and make him the choiceſt inſtrument of thy Glory, and the good of thy Church, that ever was.</p>
            <p>Thou art a good God in great faithfulneſs; doſt thou afflict us, let us learn our leſſon quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; deliver us from dulneſs and ſecurity; Lord we pray thee let inſtruction and correction go together: thou doeſt appear in thy Providence, as a God that art going about to ſit upon the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> even that is moſt precious as a Fullers fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Oh take away the droſs, that they may offer to God acceptable ſervice. It hath been much upon the thoughts of ſome of thy People, that God had a ſcourge for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry; becauſe of their failings and defects: ſend thy Spirit with thy Rod, we look upon the diſpenſation as corrections for Sin, humble Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters for their Defects, and People for their Sins.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:108768:19"/>
            <p>We look upon it as matter of Thankſgiving, and ſo have cauſe to bleſs thy Name, that thou counteſt any of us worthy to bear a teſtimony of thy Name. Lord whatſoever thou takeſt from us in this World, make it up with the Emoluments of another World; with the Incomes of thy Grace, that <hi>ſhall make us more glad, then when their Corn, Wine, and Oyl increaſeth.</hi> We have ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual wants, and it is nothing but ſpiritual reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies that will cure us; Oh be thou nigh unto us in all that we ſhall call upon thee for.</p>
            <p>Oh look upon all in affliction; upon thoſe that have begged our Prayers; the Lord be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to them, lay no more on them, then thou ſhalt enable them to bear; thoſe that complain of unprofitablenefs under the means of Grace, Lord convince them, convert them, turn their hearts, <hi>take away the ſtony heart, and give them a. heart of fleſh:</hi> take away the old rotten diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and give them a ſoft and flexible.</p>
            <p>Be in the midſt of all Congregations this day met together in the faith, and fear of the Lord; we beg that thy ſervants who have had the ſeal of their Miniſtry, may now at their departure prove powerful Inſtruments in thy hands of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="tcp:108768:19"/>good to their people.</p>
            <p>Oh let them deſtroy more luſts, more tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; beget, quicken, and raiſe up in the hand of thy Spirit, more Sons and Daughters unto the Lord this laſt time, then in all their lives before.</p>
            <p>Be with us in this Congregation, prepare our hearts to handle thy <hi>Word, which is able to ſave our ſouls;</hi> give us ſuitable affections, propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable abilities, both in Soul and Body. Do thou the work, thou ſhalt have the glory. Let Satans Kingdom at this time loſe a little ground, that thoſe who are yet in a Chriſtleſs condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may now make up the match between Chriſt and their poor ſouls. And for thoſe who have given up themſelves to Jeſus Chriſt, and yet have back-ſlidden from him; let them this evening be recovered, and give up themſelves to Jeſus Chriſt in an everlaſting Covenant; and and in a day of Confeſſion, take a part with God, and ſide with a power of Godlineſs, againſt all things that hinder.</p>
            <p>Carry thy ſervant through his work at this time, remove corruptions, give in grace; let not thy word come as a ſlight thing, but with a
<pb facs="tcp:108768:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>deep and ſerious impreſſion upon every one of our hearts, and all for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, but dear Redeemer; To whom with thee, and thy Bleſſed Spirit, be aſcribed as is moſt due, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Glory, Power, and Praiſe, now and to all Eternity. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:108768:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
